你沒被跟蹤?
You weren't followed?
沒有
No.
還是進來吧
Better come in.
吉姆 別信任任何人
Trust no one, Jim.
尤其是大人物
Especially not in the mainstream.
坐吧
Sit down.
我知道你還有一個匈牙利的身份可用
I understand you still have one H ungarian identity running?
是的
I do.
我想派你去布達佩斯
I want you to go to Budapest.
這是秘密任務
'This is not above board.
沒有其他人知道
'Nobody else knows.
他們要取我的命 吉姆老弟
'They're after my head, Jim boy.
你明白嗎?
'Do you understand?
我得到一個情報
'I have had an offer of service.
一個匈牙利的將軍
'A Hungarian general wants to come over.
我想讓你跟他碰面
'I would lik e you to meet him.'
他有我想要的信息 吉姆
He has some information that I need, J im.
什么信息?
What information?
寶藏
Treasure.
他知道蘇聯人安插在英國情報機關的內線的名字
'He has the name of the mole
'the Russians have planted in the British intelligence service
他們都是圓場高層 （圓場：英國情報機構的代稱，位于劍橋圓場）
'right at the top of the Circus.
這些爛蘋果 吉姆
'There's a rotten apple, Jim.
我們要把他找出來
'We have to find it.'
來點燉雜肉吧？嘗過這個沒？
是的，我嘗過
這東西很好，比燉牛肉要強 但是你現在在布達佩斯吃不到了
為什么？
因為那些豬都去莫斯科了
我何時能見到你的朋友？
你會見到的，不吃點嗎？
容我失陪一下
住手!
Stop!
誰讓你開槍的？
誰他媽的讓你開槍的？
你會為我做見證嗎?
Would you witness this for me?
我希望能做得更多 老總
I wish I could done more, Control.
你已經盡力了 潘西
You did all you could, Percy.
哎 一個人應該知道什么時候退場
Well, a man should know when to leave the party.
史邁利呢?
What about Smiley?
史邁利和我一起走
Smiley is leaving with me.
你這個滑頭 伊斯特哈斯
You little prick, Esterhase.
《鍋匠 裁縫 士兵 間諜》
各位 我們可以開始了嗎?
Gentlemen, shall we start?
副部長拉康已經在等您了 潘西先生
U nder Secretary Lacon is ready for you, Sir Percy.
財政部不懂
The Treasury don't understand.
為什么情報局不能直接申請
Why can't the intelligence service simply put in a request
普通的增撥資金
for a general increase in funding
那不就可以支持你們的特殊任務了嗎?
and then you account for the spend on your special operation?
“巫術行動”需要保密
Operation Witchcraft needs to remain secret.
-它有自己的一套 -這正是我們擔心的
- It's a fiefdom of its own. - Yes, that's what's worrying us.
這整一件事讓人摸不著頭腦 不是嗎?
The whole thing's very unaccountable, isn't it?
這個房子在倫敦哪兒大家都不知道
And this London house that nobody knows the address of,
真的有這個需要嗎?
is that really necessary?
絕對有必要 要保護我們在蘇聯的線人
Now more than ever. We need to protect our Soviet source.
你要我們在哪里跟他碰面? 咖啡店嗎?
So where do you propose we meet? In a caf?
這房子的租金和花費差不多是平常的兩倍
The rent and rates on this house have doubled.
在核武上就花了好幾百萬
We spent millions on nuclear warheads.
我們不過要幾千塊租個房子
We're asking for a few thousand for a house.
我好奇卡拉在克里姆林宮里 （卡拉：蘇聯情報機構頭目）
I wonder if Karla has the same problem
是不是有著同樣的煩惱
with the Treasury at the Kremlin.
聽好 沒有人低估
Look, nobody underestimates
你們工作的重要性
the importance of the job you chaps are doing.
但去年在布達佩斯發生的事
But what happened in Budapest last year,
那簡直是一個災難
that was a disaster.
坦白說
With respect, sir,
被殺的人不是你們辦公室里的公務員
it wasn't one of your civil servants that got killed, was it?
現在說的也不是戰壕里的士兵
Now this isn't about soldiers in trenches any more.
-是我們在前線的... -羅埃!
- We're the front line now... - Roy!
25年以來 我們唯一一次可以走近卡拉
For 25 years we've been the only thing standing between them and Karla
走近莫斯科 甚至走近了他媽的第三次世界大戰
and Moscow and the third bloody world war.
聽好了 大臣非常滿意你們目前的成果
Look, the Minister's very pleased with your progress so far.
不過 他對你們
He's less pleased, though,
跟美國人缺少協作這點不甚滿意
with the lack of progress with our American cousins.
你看
You see,
在他們的眼里
in their eyes,
你們還是爛船一艘
you're still a leaky ship.
怎樣?
Yes?
電話有人找你 長官 像是急事
'Someone on the line for you, sir. Seems urgent. '
好的 把電話接進來
All right, well put him through.
-喂? -是副部長拉康嗎?
- Hello? - 'Ls this U nder Secretary Lacon? '
是的
Yes.
我叫里基·塔爾
My name's Ricki Tarr.
-你想怎樣? -我要見你
- 'What do you want? ' - I need to meet you.
如果你想確認我的身份 可以去找我在圓場里的上司
If you need to confirm who I am, you can talk to my boss at the Circus,
彼得·吉勒姆
Peter Guillam.
只能是吉勒姆 不能找別人
But only Guillam, no one else.
都處理掉了嗎?
You got clearance for that?
我不負責在外面捉人
Well, I'm not bloody chaining it up outside.
我提醒你 這里也許已經不安全了 到處是刺客
Mind you, no better off in here with this bunch of bloody cut-throats.
連他們的牙齒里也藏著武器
They'd have the gold out of your teeth.
我比布蘭德早一步瞅到一個新來的女孩 他見過她沒?
Thought I'd pop in and catch a glimpse of the new girl before Bland gets to her.
啊 對 金發美女 貝琳達
Ah, yes. Belinda the blonde.
-他見過她沒? -他當然見過了
- Has he seen her yet? - Of course he has.
今早一來到的這兒的頭等大事
Came down first thing this morning.
貝琳達
Belinda.
-彼得·吉勒姆 -喂 彼得 我是奧利弗
- Peter Guillam. - 'Hello, Peter, this is Oliver.
我打電話來問一下...
'Just ringing to find out...
'So Winston Churchill saved your life, Edie.'
'I was working in the kitchen, getting dinner ready.
'And he was late, you see.'
- 'During a raid? ' - 'During a raid, you see.'
'He said, "Why aren't you in that shelter?"'
- 'Why weren't you? ' - 'Well, because... '
老總的事 我很遺憾 史邁利先生
I was sorry to hear about Control, Mr Smiley.
他說塔爾從電話亭打電話給他
'He said Tarr called him from a phone box.'
他說有只地鼠
He said there's a mole,
潛伏在圓場的高層
right at the top of the Circus,
已經好幾年了
that he's been there for years.
這就意味著
It does mean
你現在相當適合幫我們調查這件事
you're rather well placed to look into this matter for us now,
不是嗎?
doesn't it?
作為一個局外人
Outside the family.
我已經退休了 奧利弗
I'm retired, Oliver.
你炒了我
You fired me.
事實上
The thing is,
之前老總還在的時候
some time ago before Control died,
他跟我提過類似的想法
he came to me with a similar suggestion.
圓場有地鼠
That there is a mole.
他沒有跟你提起過他的猜疑嗎?
He never mentioned his suspicions to you?
沒有
No.
我只是以為.... 你是他的人
Oh, I just thought that as you were his man, so to speak...
你怎么回應他的?
What did you say to him?
我當時以為他犯了偏執病
I'm afraid I thought his paranoia had rather gotten the better of him
打算自己拆自己的臺
and he was going to pull his whole house down.
還有布達佩斯那個爛攤子
That bloody mess in Budapest.
去他的 喬治
Damn it, George.
這是你的時代 你的輝煌
It's your generation, your legacy.
我應該想到的 如果這屬實的話 你會想...
I would have thought, if there's any truth in it, you'd want to...
彼得留下給我用吧
I'll k eep Peter.
還有那個退休警察 孟德爾
And there's a retired Special Branch man, Mendel.
我也要
I should lik e to have him.
- Lift up.
And quickly down again.
我知道有個地方 在利物浦街附近的一家小旅館
There's a place I know, sir. A little hotel near Liverpool Street.
請小心點　這是喬治王朝風格的
Be careful with it. Please. It's Georgian.
我朋友需要一個安靜的工作環境 蒲波-格雷漢姆太太
My friend wants peace and quiet in order to work, Mrs Pope Graham.
沒有干擾的環境
No disturbances.
她的真名只有格雷漢姆
Her real name is just Graham.
加上“蒲波”是為了表示等級
Added the Pope for a touch of class.
彼得 你能拿到老總公寓的鑰匙嗎?
'Peter, did you get the k eys to Control's flat? '
# And did those feet in ancient time
# Walk upon England's mountains green #
噢!
Oh!
喬治!
'George! '
喬治! 給我進來!
George, get in here!
喬治
George.
坐下
Sit down.
看看這份不知所謂的東西
Tak e a look at this nonsense.
這是蘇聯最高指揮部
Report by Soviet high command
就近期他們在黑海的海軍演習發回的報告
on their recent naval exercises in the Black Sea.
這正是海軍部向我們
Just what the admiralty has been begging us
乞求的情報
for some information on.
-你從哪里搞到的? -不是我搞來的
- Where did you get this? - I didn't.
不是我 是潘西和他的小團伙拿來的
Percy and his little cabal walk ed in with it.
-老總 這... -閉嘴
- Look, Control... - Shut up.
文風差得令人發指
Style appalling.
明顯是徹頭徹尾地瞎編亂作
Patently a fabrication from beginning to end.
-不過倒像是真的 -如果內容屬實就等于挖到了金礦
- Just could be the real thing. - Well, if it's genuine, it's gold dust.
但這個話題總是惹人猜疑
But its topicality mak es it suspect.
史邁利生性多疑 潘西
Smiley is suspicious, Percy.
從哪兒弄來的? 通過什么渠道得來?
Where did it come from? What's the access?
我的一個新線人
A new secret source of mine.
可是他怎么可能弄到…?
But how could he possibly have access?
他連最高決策層的機密都有辦法搞到
He has access to the most sensitive levels of policy-making.
我們把這個情報源稱之為“巫術”
We've named the operation Witchcraft.
史邁利 潘西和他的搭檔們已經繞過了我們
Oh, Percy and his pals bypassed us, Smiley.
直接去找部長了
Gone straight to the minister.
潘西可以對他新伙計的身份
Percy has been allowed to k eep the identity of his new friend
絕對保密
top secret.
部長與我一致認為這里充斥了太多不清不楚的事情
The minister agrees too many secrets are blown around here.
接二連三的失敗 數不清的丑聞
Too much failure, too many scandals.
-可靠的情報卻少得可憐 -潘西說到點子上了 老總
- Too little solid intelligence. - Percy does have a point, Control.
我們該對抗的是共產主義 而不是自己人
We should be fighting Communism, not each other.
這些爭斗毀了我們的名聲 也讓我們失去了同盟伙伴...
Meanwhile we're losing our reputation, our partners.
你們這些惡毒的美國佬!
Your bloody Yank s!
我們已經受夠了! 是時候改變了
We've had enough! There's going to be changes.
我們要想清楚 是要活在過去 還是要創造未來
We need to decide if want to be part of the past or part of the future.
從哪兒來的給我滾回哪兒去
I should have left you where I found you.
-聽好! -老總...
- Look! - Control...
滾! 全都給我滾!
Out, all of you!
如果“巫術情報”是真的...
If Witchcraft is genuine...
再也沒有東西是真的
Nothing is genuine any more.
喬治...
George...
你要我把東西搬到旅館去嗎?
Do you want me to get this stuff over to the hotel?
謝謝 隨便放
Thank you. Er, anywhere will do.
-彼得? -嗯?
- Peter? - Hm?
彼得 我需要你幫我做點事...
I need you to do something for me.
你到圓場去
I'd lik e you to go to the Circus.
在當值室里的文件柜里
'Ln the cabinet at the duty officers' station
放著近期退休人員的記錄
'are records of staff recently retired.
你拍成照片拿給我
'I'd like photographs of them
還有潘西·阿勒萊恩著手重組的圓場架構圖表
'and of the diagram of the Circus's reorganisation under Percy Alleline,
別漏了秘密行動基金的支出表
'along with a list of all payments made from the Reptile fund.'
-有什么可以幫你的嗎? 比爾 -我在找老大
- Help you with anything, Bill? - I was just looking for his Majesty.
他在頂樓踱步呢
Well, he's out walking the battlements.
喔
Oh.
-聽說你出了點意外 彼得 -對啊 被抽屜拉手弄傷了
- Heard you had an accident, Peter. - Yeah, I cut my hand open on a drawer.
你們什么時候能在這里添些新家具啊?
When are you going to get some new furniture up here?
我會跟伊斯特哈斯反映的
I'll have a word with Esterhase. We'll mak e it a priority on the top floor.
我們樓上的人會優先考慮這件事
-你要去哪兒? -吃午飯
- Where are you off to? - Lunch.
一起好嗎?
Want some company?
根據人事文件
According to the personnel files,
有七個人是夠年齡退休
seven were due for retirement anyway.
其他四個人也看不出可疑的地方
Another four don't seem particularly mysterious.
杰里·威斯特貝在12月4日被解職
Jerry Westerby was dismissed December 4.
康妮·沙赫斯11月28日退休
Connie Sachs retired November 28.
也就是你和老總被迫出局兩周以后
That's just two week s after you and Control were forced out.
-回牛津 謝謝 -在一點十五分
- Return to Oxford, please. - That's 1. 15.
潘西一向反對
Percy has always resisted any proposal
擴大“巫術情報”的使用范圍的提議
of a wider exploitation of Witchcraft's intelligence.
別給我扯官腔 拉康
Drop the bloody jargon, Lacon.
時至今日 我還是拒絕跟我們的盟國分享“巫術”情報 大臣
I've refused to share Witchcraft with our allies so far, Minister.
貪婪的家伙
Greedy boy.
毫無疑問地我的目標在一步一步地實現
My goal has been to establish its track record beyond all doubt.
我看現在是時候去找我們的美國戰友了
I think the time has come to approach our American brothers-in-arms.
他們會再次拉我們入伙嗎?
- Will they tak e us back into bed? - I'm not interested in a one-off trade.
只做一次的買賣我沒興趣
我要的是能長期接觸到美國的情報
I want on-going access to American intelligence.
你認我們能辦到么?
You think we can get it?
只要掌握了“巫術”情報
With Witchcraft on our side, we can get anything we bloody well want.
我們想要得到什么都不成問題
好
Fine.
去做吧
Carry on.
謝謝
Thank you.
And I strik e thee down...
噢 我...
Oh, I, er...
不能喝酒的 醫生的命令
Not supposed to. Doctor's orders.
討厭的喬治
Wicked, wick ed George.
我不知道你怎么樣 喬治
I don't know about you, George,
反正我覺得親臨其境
but I feel seriously under-fuck ed.
我聽說安恩又離開你了
I heard Ann left you again.
她不配擁有你 喬治
She doesn't deserve you, George, not one hair on your head.
連你的一根頭發都不配 根本都不配
我退休后不久你就離開了圓場
You left the Circus shortly after I retired.
不是我要離開 我是被炒的
I didn't leave. I was dismissed.
像垃圾一樣被扔了 跟你一樣
Chuck ed out on the rubbish heap, lik e you.
什么理由?
Why?
波里雅科夫
'Polyak ov.
你記得他嗎?
'Do you remember him? '
蘇聯大使館的人
'From the Soviet Embassy? '
阿里克塞·波里雅科夫
'Alexsey Polyak ov, cultural attach?here in London.
在倫敦的文化參事 - 波里雅科夫
十五年前他來到的時候
'When he arrived here 15 years ago, I requested he be check ed out.
是我提出要查他的
對波里雅科夫的評級比洗衣粉還白 沒必要查
'He was graded whiter than white. Didn't put a foot wrong.'
但是你不認同?
'But you disagreed? '
你肯定聽過一個傳言
'There's a story you must have heard
卡拉組織了一個秘密組織
'that Karla has set up a secret cell.
成員都是前軍人
'The personnel are all ex-military,
專門受訓從事深入滲透的特工 地鼠
'trained to handle deep-penetration agents, moles.'
傳言從來就沒消停過 康妮
'There are always stories, Connie. '
但如果那些傳言是真的呢?
'But what if this story was true?
在研究中心的某個晚上 我看到了些東西 喬治
'One night in research I saw something, George.
我們的好朋友波里雅科夫在柏林的“五一閱兵”禮上
'There was our friend Polyak ov at a May day parade in Berlin
接受敬禮
'receiving a salute.'
為什么要向一個文化參事敬禮?
'Why would you salute a cultural attach? '
莫非波里曾是戰場上的前輩?
'Exactly. Unless he was a war veteran himself.'
如果是真的 他為什么要隱瞞呢?
And if he was, why hide the fact?
那你怎么做了?
What did you do?
我直接走到伊斯特哈斯和阿勒萊恩面前
I went straight to Esterhase and Alleline.
這里
Here.
如果我沒弄錯的話 波里雅科夫是卡拉訓練的爪牙
Polyak ov is a Karla-trained hood if ever I saw one.
如果他在這里出現 那他肯定是安插了地鼠
If he's here, it must be because he's running a mole.
你不要再管波里雅科夫的事
You're to leave Polyak ov alone.
你對他有點著迷了
You're becoming obsessed with him.
-你現在做事掌握不了分寸 -太荒謬了!
- You're losing your sense of proportion. - But that's ridiculous.
也許你是時候離開 回到現實世界中去了
Perhaps it's time you went out into the real world.
但又有什么關系呢? 圓場的老人已經散的差不多了
What does it matter? Old Circus is gone anyway.
看看這個
Here we are.
年少無知的我們
The N ursery in our day.
吉姆·普萊多
Jim Prideaux.
和比爾·海頓 兩個人必定站到一塊兒
And Bill Haydon. Together, of course.
形影不離
The Inseparables.
這是老總
There's Control himself.
大家都在
All my boys.
就像一個大家庭
All my lovely boys.
真是一段美好時光啊 喬治
That was a good time, George.
那可是戰爭啊 康妮
一場真正的戰爭
A real war.
會讓英國人感到自豪
Englishmen could be proud then.
那么 我是對的?
So I was right, then?
波里雅科夫的事
About Polyak ov.
有地鼠?
There is a mole.
如果沒處理好 就別來告訴我了
If it's bad, don't come back. I want to remember you all as you were.
我想把記憶定格在以前那個樣子
潘西 這是你干的好事嗎?
Percy? Percy, did you mix this?
哎呀 是我干的
Aye, I did so.
你這個吝嗇的蘇格蘭佬
You Calvinistic, penny-pinching Scot.
你就不能向外訂餐嗎?
Can you nae learn to tak e a bloody order?
自己胡亂擺弄什么菜譜啊!
Nobody tampers with the recipe!
-我的確是按菜譜做的 -來
- I followed the recipe. - Come on.
跟猴子尿一樣 得喝上五個小時才會喝醉
It'll tak e us five hours to get drunk on this monk ey's piss.
# He's not the first
好吧
- # He's not the first - Oh, well.
圣誕快樂!
- # He's the second best secret agent - Merry Christmas.
# I n the whole wide world
# He's not number one
# But not the worst
# He's just the second best secret agent
# I n the whole wide world
# He's every bit
# As good as what's-his-name
# With a dame
# Any dame
# And all those bullet holes are in his vest
# To prove you work a little harder
# When you're second best... #
-P夫人向你問好 -嗯?
- Courtesy of Mrs P. - H m?
你一夜沒睡?
You been up all night?
是的
Yes.
那是什么?
What's this?
申請書 請求從秘密行動經費里提取一千磅現金
Request for ?1,000 in cash from the Reptile fund.
給一個叫埃利斯的人
To a Mr Ellis.
吉姆·普萊多的其中一個化名
It was one of J im Prideaux's work names.
普萊多一年前在匈牙利被殺了
Prideaux was killed in H ungary a year ago.
10月21日
October 21.
怎么會有人在他死后兩個月給他一千磅呢?
So why was someone giving him ?1,000 two months later?
我在想他現在在哪兒呢?
I wonder where he is then, sir.
別鬧了
Settle down now.
-發下去 -先生
- Hand those out. - Sir.
什么玩意啊? 我們的駝子老師?
What is it? The H unchback of Notre-Dame?
叮叮當 叮叮當!
The bells, the bells!
噢!
- Ohh!
過來這里
Come here.
-你叫什么來著? -羅奇 我叫比爾·羅奇 先生
-我是新來的 -新來的 嗯?
- I'm a new boy. - New arrival, eh?
-你什么來歷? -我父母...
- What's the story? - My mother and father.
我爸離開了 所以...
My father left, so...
嗯
Hm.
賬單 （Bill還有賬單的意思）
Bill.
欠費賬單
The unpaid Bill.
-有人這么叫過你么? -沒有 先生
- Anyone ever call you that? - No, sir.
我認識不少人叫比爾
Known a lot of Bills in my time.
都是不錯的家伙
They've all been good 'uns.
你有些什么本事呢?
What are you good at?
沒什么 先生
Nothing, sir.
你是個不錯的觀察者 是嗎?
You're a good watcher, though, eh?
孤獨的人都善于觀察
Us loners always are.
我敢說 比爾·羅奇是班里最好的觀察員
Best watcher in the unit, Bill Roach is, I'II bet.
只要他戴上眼鏡就沒什么能逃過他的眼睛 對么?
- Long as he's got his specs on. Right? - Yes, sir.
是的 先生
這個好 非常好
This is good, very good.
在嗎 里基
Hello, Ricki.
你丟了一個楔子
You've missed the wedge.
你去了哪了? 里基
Where have you been, Ricki?
他們要殺我
They're going to kill me.
-誰要殺你? -你們
- Who is? - Your lot.
你們 或者他們 被誰先找到就死在誰手上
Or their lot. Whoever gets me first.
我是無辜的
I'm innocent.
說得過去吧
Within reason.
我會盡力 你在這多久了?
How long have you been here?
抱歉 我已經沒有地方可以躲了
Sorry, I've run out of places now.
我要見你
I needed to see you.
為什么?
Why?
有一個女人
There's a woman.
我要你把她換回來 從卡拉手上把她換回來
I need you to trade for her. I need you to get her back off Karla.
什么女人?
A woman?
她叫伊琳娜
Her name's Irina.
在去年的12月
'This was last November.
吉勒姆先生派我去伊斯坦布爾查一個俄國貿易代表
'Mr Guillam sent me to Istanbul to check out a Russian trade delegate
一個可能會轉投我們的人
'who might be persuaded to defect.'
-塔夫蒂·西辛格 駐外代表 -嗯
'Tufty Thesinger, resident.' - 'Yeah.'
-喂 里基 -最近好嗎? 兄弟
- H iya, Ricki. - All right, mate?
你認識他? 不 從來見過
'Did you know him? ' 'No, never met him.'
酒鬼一個
'Bit of a drink er.'
整天醉醺醺的
Hangover from hell.
一個蠢貨
'Bit of a fucking idiot.
這個叫鮑里斯的俄國佬
'Apparently this Russian, name of Boris,
在夜總會夜夜笙歌
'was spending high and wide in the nightclubs. '
你的任務就是游說他倒戈?
'So you were sent to persuade this Boris? '
沒錯 他是典型的俄國佬
'Yeah. He was your typical Russian.
貿易代表團就知道沒日沒夜地飲酒作樂
'Trade delegation by day, out boozing every night.
好像都不用睡覺似得
'Didn't seem to sleep.
他們幾乎都能認出塔夫蒂了 所以他不方便跟蹤
'Tufty was worn out from following him around.'
我看今晚有的忙了 孩子
I think it's going to be a long night, son.
在塔克西姆 他最愛去的地方就是俱樂部
'His favourite haunt was this club in Tak sim.
那兒的地下室是藏污納垢的地方
'Lt had a hellhole in the basement where the sailors and the tourists went.
供水手和旅客消遣的地方
反正我看了他一眼 就知道自己白來了
'Anyway, I took one look at him and I knew I'd wasted a journey.
鮑里斯不是什么代表
'Boris was no delegate.
比起代表團 他們更符合酒鬼這個身份
'What delegate bothers to play drunk er than he really is?
你得面對現實 不是嗎? 史邁利先生
'You get to recognise your own, don't you, Mr Smiley?
鮑里斯就是個流氓
莫斯科中心出來的人 （莫斯科中心：指蘇聯情報機構）
'Moscow Centre trained.'
# Someone is waiting
# I mean just for you
# Spinning wheel
# Keep on spinning through, Drop all your troubles... #
我猜他在等著接頭
'I guessed he was waiting for a connect.
或許在干投信的活兒
'Working a letterbox, maybe.
或許放線釣魚 等著像我這樣的人上鉤
'Or trailing his coat and looking for a pass from some mug like me.'
所以第二晚我就去了進出口部
'So the second night I went to the import/ export outfit
塔夫蒂在密室架了一臺加密電報機
'that Tufty had set up with a cipher room hidden in the back.
我給吉勒姆先生發了電報 “沒有交易”
'I cabled "No sale" to Mr Guillam.
就是這樣了
'And that was that.'
你第二天就要搭飛機回去
You were due to fly home the next day.
是
Yes.
但你沒回去
But you didn't.
鮑里斯有個妻子
'Boris had a wife.
合法的妻子
'Common-law.
明顯她也是代表團的成員之一
'Apparently she was a member of the delegation in her own right.
你曾經叫我相信自己對女人的直覺 史邁利先生
'You once told me to trust my instincts about women, Mr Smiley.
沒錯 我的直覺告訴我這個女人藏著寶藏
'Well, my instincts told me this woman had some treasure.
有一晚鮑里斯不在酒店 我就探入了她住的旅館
'When Boris went out for the night, I found myself going into her hotel.'
所以你丟下了鮑里斯
'So you dropped Boris.'
我知道 那不合規矩
'I know. It was breaking protocol.
但可以說是我不由自主地行動起來
'But I was acting on my own initiative, as it were. '
你的男人就是個混賬東西 不是嗎?
Your man's a bit of a bastard, isn't he?
我只是想確認一下你沒事 明白嗎?
I just wanted to mak e sure you were all right, OK?
所以你就沒有回來了?
'So you didn't come home? '
我本打算回來的
I would have.
鮑里斯那邊是沒門了 但是...
Boris was a dead end, but...
呃...
Um...
我能
I could...
我能感覺到她心里有事
I could sense something in her.
一個秘密
A secret.
你打算用什么方法把她的秘密套出來?
And how did you intend to get this secret out of her?
我用商人邁克·特侖奇的身份
'I played this businessman, Michael Trench.
跟她發生了一段假期戀情
'Holiday romance.'
可惜時間緊迫無法好好享受…
'I thought I'd tak e my time with it.'
我知道你是誰
I know who you are.
我有話要跟你們的上司談
I want to talk to your boss.
老總
Control.
我有東西跟你們做交易
I have something to trade.
很重要的東西
Something big.
我想在西方開始新的生活
I want a new life in the West.
這就是我的開價
That's the deal.
你去告訴他們
You tell them.
你不能指望他們一下子就接受所有的開價
Look, you can't expect them to jump at every offer of service.
既然你不愿多說 那我也無能為力
If you won't tell me more, there is nothing I can do.
如果我向你坦白所有
If I tell you everything,
就等于把自己的性命交到你手上
I'm putting my life in your hands.
還有其他人的生死
And the lives of other people.
她告訴我她想要的是什么
'So she told me what she had to trade.
她的秘密
'Her secret.
我指的是
'I mean,
是所有秘密的源頭
'the mother of all secrets.
我告訴她我意識到是關于圓場的
'I told her I'd alert the Circus.
她要我保證不會向倫敦透漏任何細節
'She made me promise I wouldn't give any of the details to London.'
-然后你同意了? -是的
'And you agreed? ' 'Yes.
我告訴你...
'I mean it was...
我都不敢相信自己掌握了這么重要的情報
'I couldn't believe I'd got hold of something this big.
我回到進出口部
'I went back to the import/ export,
給圓場發了個消息 標注為“最高緊急級別”
'sent the message to the Circus, graded, "Flash, highest priority",
只是說 我找到了一個想叛變的莫斯科間諜
'just that I had a Moscow-trained hood wanting to defect.'
你怎么還沒走 倫敦站的人找上我了
You're supposed to have gone. London stations have been on to me.
他們要知道你到底在玩什么花樣
Want to know what the hell you're doing.
滾你的
Fuck off.
還有嗎? 里基
'Anything else, Ricki? '
我知道 對于圓場來說 我不過是剝頭皮組的一個嘍羅 （剝頭皮組：圓場內負責搞暗殺、綁架、訛詐的機構）
I know what I am to the Circus. I'm one of the scalp-hunters,
做的是低賤卑鄙的差事
someone that you can hand your dirty little jobs to.
只是...
I just...
這件事我想由自己來解決
I just wanted to bring this one in myself.
我知道你的感受
Well, I understand how you felt.
你不想這么傻等著
You wanted to do something.
我匯報說 她聲稱掌握了
事關圓場生死的情報
Vital to the safeguarding of the Circus.
還有別的嗎?
Anything more?
我還說了 她掌握的情報是關于雙面間諜的
I said that she had information concerning a double agent.
我不過是想...得到足夠重視 我想...
Look, I just wanted to get the proper attention. And I'd...
我讓他們轉告吉勒姆先生 這是我沒有回去的原因
I told them this was the reason why I had not come home.
而不是因為我叛變了
It wasn't that I'd defected or anything.
-接下來你做了什么? -等著他們回復
- What did you do then? - I waited for a reply.
我就等了幾個小時 我聽到在黎明前的禱告
'I hung around for hours. I heard the lmsak call to prayer.
那是幾點呢? 大約在凌晨的三點三十分
'So what's that? That's about 3. 30 in the morning.'
然后消息就發過來了
'Then the message comes through.
“知道了”
"'We read you."
那就是他們發過來的 什么也沒用
'That was all they sent. Nothing.
根本說不通 像是他們在拖延時間
'Lt didn't mak e sense. It was lik e they were stalling.'
然后的事呢?
'Then what happened?
接下來 突然間...
'Then, all of a sudden...
...俄國佬開始行動了
'... the Russians begin to move.'
干的很漂亮 比我干的漂亮多了
'Lt was nice work. I couldn't have done it better myself.'
信號非常明顯 我要警告她
'The message was quite clear. I needed to warn her. '
快接 快接 快接
Come on, come on, come on.
我四處尋找 我在飛機場找不到她
'I couldn't find her at the airport.
我甚至查了一遍航班表...
'I even look ed through all the flight lists and...
我跑去了碼頭
'I headed down to the harbour.
他們把她帶上了去敖德薩的船
'They put her on a ship to Odessa.
我就知道這些了
'That's all I know.'
我已經...
I've...
我已經盡了全部的努力 史邁利先生 但是...
I've done a lot of things in my life, Mr Smiley, but...
我就是... 情不自禁地一直想著她
I just... I can't stop thinking about her.
她根本就不是我喜歡的類型
She wasn't even my type.
我想把她救出來 是我欠了她
I've got to get her out. I owe her that.
卡拉不會放過你
Karla will be looking for you.
有誰會放過我呢?
Everybody's looking for me.
你不可以留在這里
You can't stay here.
不安全
It isn't safe.
我說過 你可以上我的床 貝琳達 但是白天必須喊我長官
'I said, "You may fuck me but you'll call me "Sir" in the morning."'
知道了 就是來告訴你一聲
'OK. Just need to let you know.
上個星期有人用我們的掩護身份飛到了巴黎
'Someone flew into Paris last week on one of our escaped passports.'
-還有呢? -是里基·塔爾
'And? ' 'lt was Ricki Tarr.'
為什么要告訴我?
'Why are you telling me? '
-不過是巧合... -你這個臭侏儒
- 'Lt could be coincidence... ' - 'You are a poisoned dwarf.
為什么不死去找大臣呢?
'Why don't you fuck off to his Majesty
別想把我拉進你們的小丑團
'and stop trying to involve me in your cabaret? '
伊斯特哈斯先生 也許是巧合 但是...
'Mr Esterhase: "It could be coincidence but..."
海頓先生打斷了對話
'Mr Haydon interrupting.
你真是個臭侏儒 托比
"'You really are a poisoned dwarf, Toby.
為什么不死去找大臣呢?
"'Why don't you fuck off to his Majesty
別想把我拉進你們的小丑團
"'and stop trying to involve me in your cabaret?"'
你樣子很疲憊
You look tired.
睡得不好
I didn't sleep well.
我想要你幫我拿點東西 彼得
You're going to do something for me, Peter.
我需要值班室去年11月的登記簿
I need the duty officer's log book for last November.
我不得不讓你跑一趟樓上的虎穴
I'm going to have to send you up a floor into the lions' den.
如果你被抓到了
If you're caught,
不能把我供出來
很抱歉 不過你得孤身奮戰
I'm sorry, but you're alone.
-去年11月的? -嗯
- Last November? - Hm.
吉勒姆先生!
Mr Guillam!
謝謝 布萊恩特
Thank you, Bryant.
家里還好么?
How's the family?
很好 今天需要上去辦點事
Fine. Need to go up to the registry today.
明白 先生
OK, sir.
現在你要給包貼上黃色標簽 先生
Now you'll need a yellow one for the bag, sir.
謝謝
Thank you.
-早上好 吉勒姆先生 -早 阿爾文
- Good morning, Mr Guillam. - Morning, Alwyn.
-需要我幫你看著包么? -謝謝
- Want me to look after that for you? - Thank you.
得給你貼個標簽 吉勒姆先生
I'll need your chit, Mr Guillam.
否則道爾芬會罵死我 新規定
Dolphin will kill me if I don't. New rules.
貼吧
So, chit me.
謝
Thank s.
-真是驚喜啊 -彼得
- Sal, lovely surprise. - Peter.
-這周末有安排么? -還不那樣
- What are you up to this week end? - Oh, you know.
去看我阿姨
Visiting aunts.
猜就是
I'll bet.
通道D
Corridor D.
二十八號在右手邊的中間
The two eights are halfway on your right.
三十一號在下一個小間里
The three ones are next alcove down.
多謝
Thank s.
'Here's a request from Libby Barr from Bromley
'for "Mr Wu's A Window Cleaner Now". Tak e it away, George.'
你好 檔案館 我是阿爾文
Hello. Archive, Alwyn speaking.
麻煩你 我找一下吉勒姆先生
'Can I speak to Mr Guillam, please? '
我是修車師傅
I'm his car mechanic.
好的 我看看他有沒有空接電話 請稍等
Well, I'll just see if he's available. Hold on, please.
# Mr Wu, what shall I do?
-噢 天啊! -電話找您 先生
- Oh, Christ! - Telephone, sir.
-誰啊? -外線電話 先生 說話聲沙啞
- Who is it? - Outside line, sir. Someone rough.
先生?
Sir?
-喂? -你的齒輪箱廢掉了
- Hello? - (Mendel) 'Your gearbox is bust, sir.'
去他媽 你就不能去修一修嗎?
Damn it, can't you fix the bloody thing?
沒法修了
'Can't be done, sir.
恐怕你要換一個新的齒輪箱
好歹先找一下經銷商 你有他們的號碼嗎?
Well, phone the main dealership first. Have you got their number?
沒有
'No.'
別掛線 阿爾文!
Hang on. Alwyn!
-阿爾文 -在
- Alwyn. - Sir?
包遞給我 可以嗎?
Get me my bag, will you?
-但是... -就一下子
- But... - J ust for a second.
謝了
Thank you.
別掛線
Hang on.
-喂? -我聽著
- Hello? - 'I'm listening.'
-嗯 9-4-6 0-3-3-5 -記好了 先生
- Yes. 9-4-60-3-3-5. - 'Be right on it, sir.'
謝謝
Thank you.
彼得·吉勒姆
Peter Guillam.
你還真是難找啊
Could we see you, please?
潘西有急事跟你說
Percy would lik e quite an urgent word with you.
你現在去一下六樓 幫幫忙
If you can come now to the fifth floor that would be so kind.
行 沒問題
Yes, of course.
你替我把那玩意兒扔到電梯里去
Throw that into the lift for me.
把它送上三樓 省得我一直寫那些煩人的單子
Send it to the second floor, save me filling out bloody chits.
遵命 先生
Will do, sir.
你最近這些日子都在忙些什么呢...
So what have you been getting up to down there these days?
都在忙著泡妞吧
Apart from chasing our virgins.
有幾個阿拉伯人看起來挺靠譜的
A couple of Arab ploys that look quite promising.
除此之外 乒乓球也打的不錯
Apart from that, I'm getting quite good at ping-pong.
阿拉伯人
Arabs.
你可以租一個但是不能買下來 對吧 比爾?
You can rent one but you can't buy one. Right, Bill?
里基·塔爾最近怎么樣了?
How's Ricki Tarr these days?
還行 我們每天下午都在福特納喝茶
Fine. We have tea at Fortnum's every afternoon.
我要知道你跟塔爾的談話內容
I require the matter of your discussion with Tarr.
我會跟他說的 他會很高興的
I'll tell him. He'll be thrilled.
聳什么肩啊你?
What's that shrug for?
我跟你說的是你那個賣國賊
I'm talking to you about the traitor
那個在伊斯坦布爾殺了我們的人的賣國賊
who cut the throat of our man in Istanbul.
我說的是你那個爛部門的叛徒!
I'm talking to you about a defector from your own damn section.
我現在追究的是 你背著我勾結敵方的特工!
I'm accusing you of consorting with an enemy agent behind my back.
別他媽對我聳肩
Don't damn well shrug at me!
你想坐牢嗎?
How would you lik e a term in prison?
我現在已經不跟他見面了
Well, I haven't been seeing him.
你好好弄清楚事實 少跟我?嗦!
So get your facts straight and get off my back!
那我告訴你 塔爾最近剛到巴黎
So... if I told you Tarr had recently arrived in Paris,
你意外不?
would you be surprised?
塔爾做什么都不會讓我意外
No, nothing would surprise me about Ricki Tarr.
如果我告訴你 我們查到
And if I told you we happen to know ?0,000 mysteriously appeared
上個月有一筆3萬英鎊的資金
神奇地出現在他的銀行賬戶呢
in his bank account last month,
讓你驚喜不?
would that surprise you?
你的人是叛徒 吉勒姆
Your man's a defector, Guillam.
幾個月前被敵方收買了 現在他們把人送回來
Turned by the opposition months ago and now they've sent him back to us.
-什么目的? -別管什么目的
- What for? - Never mind what for.
要我們雞犬不寧 那就是目的
To muddy the water, that's what for.
放一組煙霧彈耍得我們團團轉!
To spread a whole lot of damn nonsense to get us chasing our tails.
現在關鍵是
The point is this.
他要回來了
He's heading for home.
你要是一看到他 立馬給大人們報告
The first peep from him, you come to the grown-ups.
明白嗎?
Understood?
現在在座的哪一位都可以 但不能對別的人透露!
Anyone you see around this table but not another damn soul.
出去
Get out.
彼得?
Peter?
謝謝你 貝琳達
Thank you, Belinda.
# Oh, Mr Wu
# What shall I do?
# Mr Wu... #
一切順利嗎?
All go smoothly, did it?
我要去旅館見史邁利
I need to go to the hotel to see George.
史邁利先生不在酒店 改地點了
Mr Smiley isn't at the hotel, sir. Change of venue.
喬治?
George?
吉勒姆先生...
Mr Guillam...
抱歉 我拖了那么久才回來
Sorry it took me so long to come home.
里基一直在幫我們 彼得
Ricki has been helping us, Peter.
他告訴了我們他所有的冒險經歷
He's been telling us all about his adventures.
他是個雙面間諜! 喬治!
He's a double, George.
根本沒有地鼠!
There is no mole. Whole thing's been thought up by Moscow.
整件事就是莫斯科那邊編出來的謊言
卡拉花三萬英鎊收買了他!
Karla bought him for ?0,000.
我偷這個 就因為你
I stole that because of you.
就因為他 弄得我自己監視自己
I spied on my own because of him. Do you know how that mak es me feel?
你知道我是什么感覺嗎?
里基...
Ricki...
你說你給圓場發了一封提及伊琳娜身份的電報?
you said you sent the Circus a telegram concerning Irina's information.
-沒錯 -哪一天?
- That's right. - What was the date?
他不會知道 因為根本就沒有電報
He doesn't know because there was no telegram.
-整件事都是編出來的 -11月20日
- The whole thing is a fabrication. - 20th November.
肯定是11月20號 傍晚的時候
It must have been 20th November. Evening.
'lrina k ept telling me in Moscow Centre
'everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
11月20號這一頁沒了
- 'She told me Karla... ' - November 20th is missing.
有人藏起了自己的記錄 難道你覺得
Someone is covering their track s, unless of course you think
這只是巧合?
that's just a coincidence?
那錢是怎么回事?
What about the money?
能換得他的地鼠的安全 3萬英鎊對卡拉來說不算什么
30,000 isn't so much for Karla to pay if it protects his mole.
恐怕圓場里有人知道了塔爾先生的事
I'm afraid someone in the Circus knows all about Mr Tarr
然后 用盡方法想誣陷他
and is doing everything they can to discredit him.
'... everything the Circus think s is gold is shit, made in Moscow.'
為什么不告訴我 你已經找到塔爾?
Why didn't you tell me that you had Tarr?
萬一我在圓場失手了
In case I never made it out of the Circus.
我要休息一會兒
到時候你應該也看完了吧
I suppose you've got your reading to do.
上來
Come up.
我見過他一次
I met him once.
卡拉
Karla.
在55年的時候
In '55.
莫斯科中心四分五裂
Moscow Centre was in pieces.
大量的清洗行動
Purge after purge.
他們一半的特工外逃
Half their agents were jumping ship.
我四處奔走 把他們攬回來
I travelled around, signing them up.
幾百號人呢
Hundreds of them.
其中有一個人管自己叫格茨曼
One of them was calling himself Gerstmann.
他在回俄羅斯的路上
He was on his way back to Russia
我們很確定他將會被處死
and we were pretty sure he was going to be executed.
飛機在德里停留了24小時 就在那段時間里
Plane had a 24-hour lay-over at Delhi and that's how long I had
我必需說服他投奔我們
to convince him to come over to us
別回去送死
instead of going home to die.
一個很小的房間里...
There's a little room.
我坐這兒 他坐那兒
I'm sitting here. He's sitting there.
美國人對他施了刑
The Americans had had him tortured.
他已經沒有了指甲
He had no fingernails.
熱得要命
It's incredibly hot.
我很累 只想把這事了結了然后回家
I'm very tired and all I want to do is get this over with and get back home.
當時正跟安恩鬧矛盾
Things weren't going well with Ann.
我用老套路勸他..
I give him the usual pitch.
來西方吧 我們可以給你舒適的生活
"Come to the West and we can give you a comfortable life,
在審訊之后
"after questioning."
他怎么說?
What did he say?
想想你的妻子
"Think of your wife.
你有妻子吧?
"You have a wife, don't you?
還有 我給你帶了點香煙
"Here. I brought you some cigarettes, by the way.
用我的打火機吧
"Use my lighter.
我們可以安排她與你團聚
"We could arrange for her to join you. We have a lot of stock to trade.
我們有一大批囤貨可以交易
要是你回去 她會被流放 為她考慮考慮吧
"If you go back, she'll be ostracised. Think of her.
想想...
"Think about..."
我一直...
I kept on...
...說老婆的事兒
...harping on about the damn wife,
之后跟他說了很多我自己的事...
telling him more about me than...
其實我早該起身離去
I should have walk ed out, of course.
但是出于某種原因 我覺得救出這個人很重要
我跟你其實沒有太多的不一樣
"We're not so very different you and I.
你和我花了一輩子時間
"We've both spent our lives
來尋找對方制度上的弱點
"looking for the weaknesses in one another's systems.
難道你不覺得是時候承認
"Don't you think it's time to recognise
你的一方和我的一方都是沒有東西值得我們賣命的嗎?
"there is as little worth on your side as there is on mine?"
沒說一句話
Never said a word.
一個字都沒說
Not one word.
第二天早上他坐飛機回去了
And the next morning he got back on his plane.
把那包煙還給了我 沒有碰過
He handed the pack of cigarettes back to me, untouched.
這個老煙槍
This was a chain-smok er, mind.
懷著必死的心飛走了
And he flew off to what he presumed would be his death.
他留著我的打火機
He k ept my lighter.
那是一份禮物
It was a gift.
“給喬治 安恩贈”
"To George from Ann.
“我的最愛”
"All my love."
他就是卡拉?
That was Karla.
他寧愿飛回去送死也不愿意投降?
He went back to die rather than giving in.
嗯 也就是這一次 我知道了他不是不可戰勝的
Yes, and that's how I k now he can be beaten.
他是個狂熱分子
Because he's a fanatic.
狂熱分子總是隱藏著猜疑
And the fanatic is always concealing a secret doubt.
他長什么樣?
What did he look lik e?
我記不起來了
I can't remember.
今天以后 彼得
After today, Peter,
你要小心他們在監視你
you have to assume they're watching you.
想想還有什么東西要收拾
If there's anything you need tidied up,
趁現在
now is the time.
快好了
Nearly done.
For God's sak e.
Sometimes I think they're all sharing the same moronic brain.
如果你有了別人 可以坦白告訴我
If there's someone else, you can tell me.
我是成年人了
I'm a grown-up.
我知道 這是一個快樂的圣誕節
I know. It's just going to be such a wonderful Christmas.
抱歉
Excuse me.
# And I was too proud to give in
# I had to learn the hard way
彼得 你準備好了
- # That pride... # - Peter, when you're ready
播出來
Put it on now.
大家注意!
Everybody!
-杰里 -喬治
- Jerry. - George.
-彼得 -杰里
- Peter. - Jerry.
我要跟你談談
I need to talk to you.
吉姆·普萊多被殺的那晚
About the night J im Prideaux was killed.
你是值勤員 沒錯吧?
You were duty officer, weren't you?
是的 那天晚上老總讓我負責接電話
Yeah. Control ask ed me to man the phones that night.
他說有人為圓場在執行特殊行動
He said someone was doing a special job for the service.
他要找一個信得過的人
He wanted someone he could trust.
'Hurricane Henry set to be ridden by Ray Walsh at 7:2... '
長官 出了點事
There's been a bit of a panic, sir.
消息來自英國外交部常駐書記
This is from the FO resident clerk.
一條匈牙利新聞簡報 長官
A Hungarian news bulletin.
一名化名為埃利斯的英國間諜
"British spy, work name Ellis,
使用偽造的匈牙利證件出行
"travelling with false Hungarian papers,
在布達佩斯試圖綁架一名未提及姓名的匈牙利將軍
"has attempted to kidnap an unnamed Hungarian General in Budapest.
他中槍了
"He's been shot.
其他逮捕行動也將展開
"Other arrests imminent."
長官 可以告訴我個大概嗎?
Can I have a brief, please?
長官　你要我裝聾扮啞嗎?　長官?
Sir? Do you want me to deny it, sir?
給我說個大概啊 長官
老總一點也不松口
'I couldn't get a word out of Control.
我只好依照緊急情況處理指示來做
'So I followed protocol and went for the emergency list.'
你打電話去我家
You rang my house.
想碰碰運氣看你從柏林回來了沒有
J ust on the off-chance you were back from Berlin.
你說了什么?
What did you say?
-喂 你好 -你好 史邁利太太
- 'Hello? ' - Hello, Mrs Smiley.
我是杰里 局里的杰里·威斯特貝
It's Jerry. Jerry Westerby from the office.
剛才出了點事
Just that there'd been a bit of a crisis.
她說你還沒回來 就這些了
Ann said you wasn't back yet and that was it.
接著說
Go on.
整個局面都失控了
All hell brok e loose.
軍方為匈牙利坦克在邊界的活動大為不滿
Military yelling about Hungarian tank s on the border.
Lacon and the minister baying at the door.
拉康和大臣在門口吵得不可開交
謝天謝地比爾·海頓及時出現了
Thank Christ Bill Haydon turned up when he did.
-海頓先生 -別吵
- Mr Haydon. - Not now.
海頓先生!
Mr Haydon!
出去!
Out!
-告訴我 -我有試過聯系你的
- Tell me. - I tried to get hold of you.
我在俱樂部的電報上只看到消息的一半 告訴我
I got half a story on the tick er tape at my club. Tell me.
吉姆·普萊多中槍了
Jim Prideaux's been shot.
打電話去匈牙利大使館
Get me the H ungarian embassy.
告訴你們的主子
You tell your masters what will happen
要是普萊多少了根頭發 后果很嚴重...
if one hair on J im Prideaux's head is damaged.
打電話給伊斯特哈斯 叫他召回咱們在匈牙利的特工
Get Esterhase on the phone. Tell him to call in the Hungarian agents.
是的 長官
Yes, sir.
有更多他的消息嗎? 長官
Any more news on him? Sir?
天吶
Oh, God.
還要去他的公寓 把相關的東西銷毀
We need to get down to his flat, clear out anything link ed.
海頓在他的俱樂部聽到的消息?
Haydon heard the news at his club?
在薩維爾
凌晨一點半的時候 無線電已經不工作了
At 1: 30? The tick er-tape wouldn't have been running.
那他怎么知道的?
So how did he know?
-天吶 喬治... -彼得!
- Jesus, George. - Peter!
-他怎么知道的? -這事你別去想了
- How could he have known? - It's not what you think.
-那他究竟怎么知道的? -因為那天晚上他在我的家
- Then how did he know? - He was at my house that night.
旅途愉快?
Good flight?
嗯
Yes.
很不錯
Pleasant enough.
我只是路過 想著應該拜訪一下
I was just passing. I thought I'd call in.
安恩當時在床上 但是她堅持要起來
Ann was in bed. She insisted on getting up.
她說她馬上下來
She said she'd be down in a minute.
我帶了這個過來 畫得實在夠憋腳的
That's what I'm dropping off. It's an awful daub really.
不過安恩好像挺喜歡的
But Ann expressed a liking.
她怎么還不下來?
What's k eeping her?
加油
Keep going.
加油 孩子們 堅持住
Come on, lads. Keep up.
加油 比爾!
Come on, Bill!
-眼鏡戴上了嗎? 小胖 -是的 先生
- Got your specs on, J umbo? - Yes, sir.
過來
Come here.
在那邊的人是誰?
Who's that fellow down there?
我不知道 先生
I don't know, sir.
他是誰?
Who is he?
乞丐?
Beggar man?
盜賊?
Thief?
為什么他不往這兒看?
Why doesn't he look this way, hm?
要是一群小子在空地里亂開著一輛車 你怎么會不看一眼?
Wouldn't you if you saw a bunch of boys flogging a car round a field?
他怎么了? 他不喜歡我們嗎?
What's the matter with him? Doesn't he lik e us?
別讓一些怪人晃來晃去
I don't hold with odd-bods hanging around.
他可能要把阿爾維斯偷走
He might steal the Alvis.
-那是什么啊? -英國最好的車! 先生
- Which is? - The best car in England, sir.
好孩子
Good lad.
你是怎樣接到布達佩斯的任務的?
How were you briefed for the Budapest mission?
老總把我叫到肯辛頓的公寓
Control ask ed me to come to a flat in Kensington.
這個爛蘋果 吉姆
There's a rotten apple, Jim.
我們要把它找出來
And we have to find it.
你是怎么理解的? 吉姆
What did you mak e of it, Jim?
老總的理論?
Control's theory?
我覺得老總瘋了
I thought it was madness.
我知道是他們五個中的一個
I know that it is one of five men.
你只需要告訴我他們的代號
All I want from you is one code name.
阿勒萊恩
Alleline.
鍋匠
Tink er.
海頓
Haydon.
裁縫
Tailor.
布蘭德
Bland.
士兵
Soldier.
我們不用“水手” 因為與“裁縫”的發音太接近
We drop Sailor. It's too close to Tailor.
“富人”好像不太適合
And Rich Man doesn't seem to be applicable.
伊斯特哈斯
Esterhase.
窮人?
Poor Man.
還有第五個?
And the fifth?
史邁利
Smiley.
這想法太瘋了
I thought it was madness.
竟然覺得你是他們其中的一個
To think that any one of you could have been a traitor.
徹底地瘋了
Absolute madness.
但你還是去了
'But you still went.
為什么?
'Why? '
我去 是因為老總叫我去
'I went because Control ask ed me to go.
我是履行職責
'Lt's called doing one's duty.
我在車站與那個帶我去見將軍的跑腿碰面
'At the station I met the legman supposed to tak e me to the General.
侍應生被嚇壞了
'The waiter must have panick ed.
本來是一個簡單的小任務
'Lt was meant to be a simple snatch job.
他們把我送到了軍方醫院
'They drove me to some military hospital,
然后押上了運輸機
'and then put me on a transport plane.
一開始的時候我還分得清我們向著東方走
'I could tell by the stars we were heading east.
我們一直審我...
'Then they work ed me for...
...不知道審多久了
'... I don't know how long.
幾個星期 或許幾個月
'Week s, maybe months.'
你跟他們說什么了?
What did you tell them?
所有的事
Everything.
我盡全力堅持著 為所有人爭取時間逃出匈牙利
I held on for as long as I could to let everyone get the hell out of there.
他們有逃掉嗎?
Did they?
我的人都在匈牙利 他們逃出去了嗎?
My network s in H ungary, did they get out?
沒有 他們被端了
No, they were blown.
傳聞說你為了自保 把他們都供出來了
The story is you blew them to save your own skin.
他們審完了以后 有個小個子就出現了
'After the interrogators had cleared out, this little fellow turned up.
看上去像個神父
'Look ed lik e a priest.
那才是來真格的
'That's when they really started on me.'
你最后的防線是什么?
What was your last line of defence, hm?
地鼠
The mole.
老總的瘋狂理論
Control's crazy theory.
我一直深埋著 他們決不會從我這兒套出來的
I was going to bury that so deep they'd never get it out of me.
-結果卻成了笑話 -為什么?
- Which was a jok e. - Why?
因為他們早就知道
Because they already knew.
他們想知道的是老總調查到哪一步了
All they wanted to know was how far Control had got in his investigation.
不 我不認識她
No, I don't know her.
他們問了我什么事嗎?
Did they ask about me at all?
有
Yes.
那個小個子問了
The little fellow did.
他說了我什么?
What did he say about me?
他拿著個香煙打火機
He had this cigarette lighter.
他拿著打火機我面前晃來晃去
He k ept flashing it about for me to see it.
把題詞給我看
Showed me the inscription.
“給喬治 ...” “安恩贈”
- "To George..." - "...from Ann.
“我的最愛”
"All my love."
是卡拉
Karla.
很奇怪
'lt was odd.
他們把我送回了英格蘭
'They sent me back to England.
直接到沙拉特匯報情況 （沙拉特：圓場培訓新特務的機構，位于沙拉特）
'Straight to Sarratt for debriefing.'
他說他脫身后 在護理院受審的時候 有一個人找過他
He said when he was being debriefed at the N ursery, he had a visitor.
誰?
Who?
托比·伊斯特哈斯
'Toby Esterhase.
他給了吉姆一千鎊 和一輛阿爾維斯
'He gave him ?1,000 and an Alvis.'
叫他就此人間蒸發別再回來
Told him he was dead now. Couldn't come back.
像喝了孟婆湯一樣 忘掉所有發生過的事情
Had to become a lotus eater, forget everything that happened.
包括老總的那套說法
Control's theory.
鍋匠 裁縫... 所有所有
Tink er, Tailor. All of it.
這正是我不解的地方
Yes, that's what I thought.
伊斯特哈斯究竟是如何得知“鍋匠 裁縫”的呢?
How on earth did Esterhase hear about Tink er, Tailor?
伊琳娜老是跟我說起 在莫斯科中心里
'lrina k ept telling me in Moscow Centre
大人物們那些笑得止不住的笑聲
'everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
她說卡拉非常為之驕傲
'She told me Karla was very proud of this.
圓場視為金礦的東西不過是垃圾 全是來自莫斯科
'She said everything the Circus think s is gold is shit, made in Moscow.
伊琳娜老是跟我說起 在莫斯科中心里
'Lrina k ept telling me in Moscow Centre
大人物們那些笑得止不住的笑聲
'everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
不 我知道附近有家旅館 他們有幾個小房子
'No, I had a hotel nearby. They do have some seedy rooms.
伊琳娜老是跟我說起 在莫斯科中心里
'Lrina k ept telling me in Moscow Centre
大人物們那些笑得止不住的笑聲
'everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
她說卡拉非常為之驕傲...
'She told me Karla was very proud of this... '
“圓場視為金礦的東西不過是垃圾”
'She said everything the Circus think s is gold is shit.'
不開會了 說的夠清楚沒?
This meeting is not taking place. Is that clear?
很清楚 大臣
Perfectly, Minister.
在城里的某座宅子
There is a house somewhere in this city
是阿勒萊恩和其他幾個人 跟“巫術”的倫敦代表碰頭的地方
where Alleline and the others meet Witchcraft's London representative.
我以為拉康跟你說得夠明白了
I thought Lacon had made it clear to you.
“巫術”的事你別插手!
Keep your nose bloody well out of Witchcraft's business.
我就是遵照著拉康的意思辦事
It's Lacon's advice I'm following.
是你讓我跟老總的足跡調查下去
You told me to follow in Control's footsteps.
我不管是誰的意思 老總給我們丟下這么個該死的爛攤子
I wouldn't consider that sound advice, given the mess Control left us with.
害得阿勒萊恩 不妨直說 還害我
It has tak en Alleline and, if I may say so, myself
花了多少時間才讓圓場重新走上正軌
this long to get us back in the game.
阿勒萊恩和其余幾個人要見的人正是波里雅科夫
The man Alleline and the others meet is called Polyak ov.
你以為他負責把“巫術情報”送到你手上
'From Witchcraft to you.
而實際上他是負責把地鼠的情報
'His real role is to receive information from the mole
送回給卡拉
'to tak e back to Karla.'
這...這不可能
That, er... That's not possible.
有可能
Made possible.
有你幫忙說服財政部支付了宅子的費用
By you in the house you persuaded the Treasury to pay for.
“巫術情報”千真萬確 是金礦啊!
Witchcraft's intelligence is genuine. It's been gold.
看似誘人 其實都是雞毛蒜皮的東西
It's just enough glitter amongst the chick en feed.
老總不相信奇跡 也不相信“巫術”
Control didn't believe in miracles or in Witchcraft.
但因為你的怠慢失職和貪婪
But you were lazy and greedy
就想方設法趕他出局 從而讓卡拉趁虛而入
and so you hounded him out of the Circus and you let Karla in.
你們已經跟美方展開談判 磋商交換情報的事宜
You opened negotiations to exchange intelligence with the Americans.
他們給圓場的情報也會一字不落去到克里姆林宮
What they tell the C ircus, they'll be telling the Kremlin.
“巫術”提供的所謂“金礦”情報
Witchcraft's information, the "gold" Karla let you have,
他想引誘上鉤的不是你
it wasn't to lure you.
而是美國佬
It was to lure the Americans.
現在
Now,
你還想邀功嗎?
do you want to tak e credit for that?
我們能怎么辦?
What can we do?
我們手里有一樣地鼠想要的東西
We have one thing the mole wants.
-如果要我去巴黎... -你要去...
- If I go to Paris... - You'll go.
如果要我...去巴黎
If I go to Paris,
我要你們保證把伊琳娜帶回來
I want your word that you will get Irina back.
我不管你們拿誰去換 反正我不玩了
I don't care who you have to trade. And I am out.
我想要一個家 我才不想落得你們這些人的下場...
I want a family, thank you. I do not want to end up lik e you lot.
你們把她帶回來
You will get her back.
我會盡力的 里基
I'll do my utmost, Ricki.
噢 你好 喬治
Oh, hello, George.
你好
Hello.
我想跟你談談忠誠 托比
I want to talk about loyalty, Toby.
老總招你進來的 是不是?
Control recruited you, didn't he?
他看你在維也納一個博物館里挨餓
Found you starving in a museum in Vienna.
還是通緝犯
A wanted man.
聽說他救了你一命
Saved your life, I heard.
然而 到了關鍵時刻
And yet when the time came,
讓你在老總和阿勒萊恩之間作選擇的時候
when it came to picking sides between him and Alleline,
你就沒猶豫過?
you didn't hesitate.
或許這能歸因于你經歷過戰爭
That's understandable, perhaps, with your war experience.
這么多年來你能生存下來
You survived this long, I suppose, because of your ability to change sides.
我想這跟你慧眼識主的能力不無關系
還真倒戈自如啊
Serve any master.
這話... 這話從何說起呀 喬治?
What? What's... What's this about, George?
從你改投哪方陣營說起 托比
It's about which master you've been serving, Toby.
情報泄露了 托比
'I ntelligence has been leak ed, Toby.
有人一直從圓場盜取情報
'Someone's been taking files from the Circus.
不 不 不 不 不
'No, no, no, no. No.'
這是個誤會 你誤解了
This is a mistak e, a misunderstanding.
文件都交給了一個蘇聯外交參事 是不是?
Files were delivered to a Russian attach? weren't they?
是的
Yes.
我也承認是我送出去的
'And, yes, I delivered them.'
但潘西也有份
'But so did Percy Alleline.'
好孩子
Good boy.
比爾
'Bill Haydon.
還有羅埃·布蘭德
'And so did Roy Bland.'
有些事并非如我們想象中那樣 喬治
Things aren't always what they seem, George.
你是知道的
You should know that.
蘇聯當局以為波里雅科夫...
Look, Moscow think s Polyak ov's...
...是在為他們效力
...working for them.
所以我們時不時給他點無關重要的情報帶回去充數
Every now and then we give him the odd file to tak e back to them.
都是些雞毛蒜皮的情報 算是給他上司的交代
Chick en feed, just to k eep his bosses happy.
但其實波里雅科夫是我們的人
But Polyak ov's our Joe.
-是一項大行動的關鍵人物 -你指“巫術行動”嗎?
- He's a part of a big operation. - Operation Witchcraft.
這個我知道
Yes, I know.
喬治
George.
-拜托 我不該受到這樣的待遇 -是誰派你去見吉姆
- Please, I don't deserve this. - Who gave you the message
叫他忘掉“鍋匠裁縫”的事?
for Jim Prideaux to forget about Tink er, Tailor?
-布蘭德 -那么鏟除康妮·沙赫斯的事呢?
- Bland. - To get rid of Connie Sachs?
-威斯特貝呢? -布蘭德
- Westerby? - Bland.
也許是海頓
Or Haydon.
我不記得了 反正他們其中一個
I don't know. One of them.
也可能是潘西 不
Or maybe Percy. No.
我不知道是誰
Well, I don't know who.
你只是個信差
You're just the messenger.
在他們之間跑來跑去
Running between them all.
你有為“巫師”效力嗎?
Anything to serve Witchcraft.
我非常清楚你們的終極秘密
I know all about your secret source.
我也知道你所不知道的
And I know something you don't.
我知道他是誰
I know who he is.
他就是卡拉
He's Karla.
你們中有人給了波里雅科夫貨真價實的機密情報
'One of you has been giving Polyak ov the crown jewels. '
-我不知情 -你還在通緝名單上嗎? 托比
- I did not know. - Are you still a wanted man, Toby?
-看 喬治 我真不知情 我... -你站錯隊了
- Look, George, I didn't know. I... - You pick ed the wrong side.
你得相信我 我絕不會...
No, you've got to believe me.
喬治 別
George, please.
我是忠誠的!
I am loyal.
我... 我是忠誠的!
I... I am loyal.
不要... 不要... 不要送我回去
Don't... Don't... Don't send me back.
不要 喬治
Please, George.
不要送我回去
Don't send me back.
把地址給我
Give me the address.
你們與波里雅科夫見面的地點
Where do you meet Polyak ov?
嘿 嘿! 乖狗狗 別吵!
Hey, hey! Dog, dog, be quiet!
怎么回事? 你是誰?
What is this? Who are you?
-麥克雷格太太? -是的
-安全信號是什么? -通風管道
- What are the safety signals? - The air vent.
打開的話表示一切正常 關閉則表示不能內進
Open and all's well, closed and you're not to enter.
竊聽器在哪兒?
And the microphone?
彼得?
Peter?
“男孩站在燃燒的甲板上 除他外無人生還”
The boy stood on the burning deck whence all but he had fled
“火焰照亮了戰爭的殘骸 火光中他孤零零地站在尸體堆中”
The flame that lit the battle's wreck shone brightly o'er the dead
“他的身影卻是那樣絕美而明亮 命中注定駕馭暴風之上”
'Beautiful and proud he stood as born to rule the storm
“血肉之軀 雖然渺小 卻為之驕傲”
'A creature of blood, a proud though child-lik e form'
“火焰在翻騰...”
- The flames rolled on...
謝謝 再見
Merci. Au revoir.
繼續
Go on.
局里出動了全部人馬在找你
The whole service is looking for you.
他們找到你非活剝了你的皮不可
- They'll skin you alive if they find you. - Maybe I want them to find me.
或許我希望他們找到我
你可以回家了 把書放回原處 鑰匙插到機子里
You can go now. Leave the book s and put the k eys in the machines.
不 本 你留下
No, Ben stays here.
里基·塔爾聲稱手中有更多關系圓場安危的情報
Ricki Tarr claims to have information vital to the safeguarding of the Circus.
史邁利先生?
'Mr Smiley? '
有計程車駛進圓場
Taxi approaching Circus.
鍋匠
Tink er.
裁縫
Tailor.
這個是士兵
Here comes Soldier.
人齊了
'Full house.'
好 繼續 大聲念出來
- Well, go on then. Read it out loud. - "Personal for Tarr from Alleline.
“阿勒萊恩致塔爾的私人信息”
“在滿足你的請求前我們需要澄清”
"Require clarification before meeting your request.
“前引號 更多關系圓場安危的情報 后引號”
"Quote, information vital to safeguarding of the Circus, unquote
“不足以說明情況 需提供更多的情報”
"does not qualify, send further information."
這就對了嘛 姓潘西的 你就拖延時間吧
Ah! That's it, Percy, you k eep stalling.
我得警告你 本 園場里有奸細
I warn you, Ben. We've got some really lousy people in this outfit.
你誰都不能輕信
I wouldn't trust a fucking one of them.
“會議結束”
'The meeting's over.
“他們要走了”
'They're leaving.'
克拉道克斯說我不用幾天就可以離開了
Craddox says I'll be off in a few days.
我一直在想 在莫斯科我會有多惦念板球這游戲啊
I k eep thinking how much I'm going to miss the crick et in Moscow.
我很希望你能幫我跑跑腿
I was rather hoping you might do a little light housek eeping for me.
我會盡力的
If I can.
有個女孩 你能替我給她點錢么?
There's a girl. Give her some money, would you?
幫我編個故事
And give her a good cover story.
如果能讓她好過點 就跟她說我愛她
If it helps, tell her I love her.
全在那兒了
It's all there.
還有個男孩 給他塞點堵口費
And there's a boy, too. Slip him a few quid to shut him up.
我太清楚審訊人慣用的伎倆了
I know the inquisitors' bag of trick s. I taught most of them.
他們幾乎都是我教出來的
我有點激動
It's just a reaction.
也許是太激動了 隨便你怎么想
An over-reaction, if you lik e.
我有一兩個問題
I did have one or two questions.
-關于普萊多的 -該死!
- About Prideaux. - Goddamn it!
-是我把他救回來的 不是嗎? -沒錯 是你
- I got him back, didn't I? - Yes, yes, you did.
那是你的功勞
我很意外卡拉居然沒有斃了他
I am surprised Karla didn't have him shot.
還是你覺得
Or do you think he held back,
他之所以退縮是出于對你的微妙情感?
out of delicacy towards you?
普萊多赴匈牙利執行任務前是不是去找過你?
Did Prideaux come and see you before he left on the Hungarian mission?
沒錯 事實就是這樣
Yes, as a matter of fact he did.
為了說什么嗎?
To say what?
為了警告你
To warn you.
因為他心知肚明
Because he knew deep down
那個人從始至終就是你
it was you all along.
你也一樣
So did you.
我不得不選擇立場 喬治
I had to pick a side, George.
這是個兩難的抉擇 差不多就是個道德難題
It was an aesthetic choice as much as a moral one.
西方國家越來越丑惡
And the West has become so very ugly.
你不覺得嗎?
Don't you think?
卡拉有沒有想過讓你接管圓場?
Did Karla ever consider having you tak e over the Circus?
我才不是他的走卒!
I'm not his bloody office boy!
那你是什么呢? 比爾
What are you, then, Bill?
我就是一個功成名就的人
I'm someone who's made his mark.
有什么需要我幫你帶給安恩的嗎?
Is there anything particular you want me to pass on to Ann?
喔 那只是工作需要 喬治 我想你應該能明白的
Oh, that was nothing personal, George. I hope you understand that.
卡拉說你是個厲害角色
Karla said you were good,
不容小覷
the one we had to worry about.
不過你確實也有死穴
But you do have a blind spot.
他料想如果我當了安恩的公開情人
He reck oned if I was known to be Ann's lover,
你便不那么容易能揭穿我了
you wouldn't be able to see me straight.
他是對的
And he was right.
一定程度上
Up to a point.
我給您做了樣東西 先生
I made this for you, sir.
我不想再看到你到處閑逛
I don't want you hanging around here any more.
從現在開始離我遠點
Keep away from me from now on.
-去找大伙玩吧 -但是...
- Go and join the others. - But...
叫你去... 你就去吧
Just... Just bloody join in, will you?
他媽的找他們玩去!
Go and play, damn you!
你可以查一下嗎? 杰里
Could you check, Jerry?